{"tossups": [{"question": "The most remote portion of this structure was constructed in a region whose name translates to \"horses losing their way.\" The traditional endpoints of this structure were located at the \"First Pass Under Heaven\" and the Shanhai Pass. This structure's longest segment runs from Mount Hu to Jiayu Pass. This structure originated from the unification of several smaller fortifications under the Qin Dynasty. For the point, name this extremely long series of fortifications located in northern China.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Wall</u></b> of China (or <b><u>W\u00e0nl\u01d0 Ch\u00e1ngch\u00e9ng</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man succeeded David Zakai as head of the Histadrut trade union. Lord Gort and this man led the Haganah against the Irgun during the Saison. Moshe Sharett succeeded this man, though he came back as acting prime minister to launch an attack on Syrians in Operation Olive Leaves. Immediately after this man's declaration of independence, an Arab attack was launched. West Germany compensated this man's nation after he worked with Konrad Adenauer over reparations from the Holocaust. For the point, name this first Prime Minister of Israel.", "answer": "David <b><u>Ben-Gurion</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This monarch instituted the unpopular <em>Maltolt</em>, a duty on wool, to fund a war during an interregnum period in Scotland. This man introduced English Common Law to Wales via the Statute of Rhuddlan [[RITH-lahn]] after his conquest of its final northwestern kingdoms. This monarch\u2019s wife, Eleanor of Castile, imported archers from her native Spain to assist in a conflict led by Simon de Montfort and this man, the Second Barons' War. For the point, name this 13th-century English king who was nicknamed for his height.", "answer": "King <b><u>Edward I</u></b> (accept <b><u>Edward Longshanks</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "On this mountain, a mythical cow named Rayli produces fat from its tail glands. This mountain's Great Penck Glacier has disappeared, and Hans Meyer and Ludwig Purtscheller were the first to scale this mountain. Johannes Rebmann was the first European to find this mountain, but his claims were doubted by geographers who refused to accept that snow could persist so close to the equator. In 1861, Karl Klaus von der Decken confirmed his claims first hand during an attempted summit. For the point, name this Tanzanian peak, the highest mountain in Africa.", "answer": "Mount <b><u>Kilimanjaro</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man was accompanied by Purepecha and Aztec warriors in the conquest of Juan Alem\u00e1n's tribes during the Tiguex War. Prior to an expedition by this conquistador, Friar Marcos de Niza came across the city of Quivira, whose residents presumably murdered Estevanico. Beginning at the Zuni village of Hawikuh, this man sent multiple expeditions to follow the course of the Colorado and Gila Rivers. For the point, name this Spanish explorer of the American Southwest, who unsuccessfully searched for the Seven Cities of Gold.", "answer": "Francisco V\u00e1zquez de <b><u>Coronado</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A jar with this person's supposed remains was determined by Philippe Charlier to be an Egyptian mummy. Benedict XV canonized this person in 1920, and she was posthumously retried by Callixtus III. A popular 1917 song titled \"They Are Calling You\" referenced the devotion held toward this person by soldiers of one country who carried her image into battle. Held at the castle of Rouen, this woman was captured by the Burgundians and given to the English. For the point, name this French heroine, burnt at the stake in the Hundred Years' War.", "answer": "<b><u>Joan of Arc</u></b> (or <b><u>Joan d'Arc</u></b>; accept <b><u>Jeanne d'Arc</u></b>; prompt on \"Maid of Orleans\" or \"Maid of Lorraine\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the controversial book <em>Where [this city] Once Stood</em>, Iman Jacob Wilkens postulates that a war was fought between clans of Ancient Celts in Cambridgeshire. Architect Wilhelm D\u00f6rpfeld found the sixth and seventh levels of this city dated to the 13th century BC. With Frank Calvert, Heinrich Schliemann conducted a controversial dig at this site, later attempting to sell Turkish artifacts to the Kingdom of Greece. For the point, name this semi-mythological site, the home of Paris and Hector, which was under siege during the <em>Iliad</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Troy</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ilium</u></b>; accept <b><u>Hisarlik</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Integralists attempted to overthrow this man\u2019s regime in the \u201cPajama Putsch,\u201d a night attack on Guanabara Palace. J\u00falio Prestes [[PREST-shiz]] was exiled in favor of this man after the downfall of the \u201cOld Republic\u201d during the Revolution of 1930. This Latin American leader wrote, \u201cI gave you my life, now I give you my death\u201d in the <em>Carta</em> <em>Testamento</em>, a suicide note written after his plan to assassinate Carlos Lacerda was exposed.  For the point, name this president who, in 1937, established the <em>Estado Novo</em> in Brazil.", "answer": "Getulio <b><u>Vargas</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "As a result of the 1988 Daniel Day Lewis film rendition of this work, the Nobel Prize-winning writer of this novel subsequently refused to allow his work to be adapted for film. This work of magical realism challenges Friedrich Nietzsche's concept of eternal recurrence. The historical events surrounding this work of fiction took place after the election of Alexander Dubcek [[DOOB-chek]] up to the invasion of the author's country by the Soviets in 1968. For the point, what Milan Kundera novel follows Tom\u00e1s [[toh-MOSH]] during the era of the Prague Spring?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Unbearable Lightness of Being</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This man's son was the first curator of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, developing the theory of \"architectural refinement.\" Leverett Candee was the first to take advantage of one process this man discovered. This man made a welt for shoemaking and disputed an invention with Thomas Hancock. This man worked with gum elastic, and with Nathaniel Hayward, this man found a process that combined rubber and sulfur. For the point, name this man who created waterproof rubber and developed vulcanization, for whom a large tire company is named.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>Goodyear</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The final ruler of this empire faced Demetrius I's invasion from Bactria. Dasharatha and Kunala may have split this empire according to Vincent Smith, and Dasharatha made inscriptions in the Barabar Hill Caves north of Gaya. Besides Samprati, this state was ruled by a man who fought a war in the Dhauli Hills by the Daya river, the Kalinga War, leading to that man becoming Buddhist. \"Inscriptions of Dharma\" are among this empire's Edicts of Ashoka. For the point, what Iron Age empire dominated India?", "answer": "<b><u>Maurya</u></b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This Milanese artist's powerful patrons, including Cardinal Francesco Maria del Monte, were usually able to protect him from the consequences of his violent temper, but this man's murder of Ranuccio Tommasoni forced him to flee Rome or face beheading. Perhaps not coincidentally, several of this Baroque artist\u2019s subsequent works depict beheadings such as <em>Judith Beheading Holofernes</em>. For the point, name this groundbreaking master of chiaroscuro, the creator of <em>Salome with the Head of John the Baptist</em> and <em>David with</em> <em>the Head of Goliath</em>?", "answer": "Michelangelo Merisi da <b><u>Caravaggio</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In what is now this country, forces under Cyril Clowes pushed Japanese forces to withdraw during the Battle of Milne Bay. In May 2009, fights at a nickel factory resulted in massive anti-Chinese riots in this country. In this nation, Francis Ona led the BIG in a ten-year civil war on its island of Bougainville. During the Battle of the Coral Sea, the Japanese invaded and occupied what is now this country's capital. For the point, name this Tok Pisin-speaking Melanesian nation with capital at Port Moresby.", "answer": "Independent State of <b><u>Papua New Guinea</u></b> (do not accept or prompt on \"New Guinea\" or \"Guinea\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The first stage of this process was led by a magistrate known as the <em>paidon\u00f3mos</em>, or the \u201cboy-watcher.\u201d This tradition, which began when a male turned seven, started with the semi-mythical king Lycurgus, who did not allow the boys to bathe and gave them one set of clothes. Many of this program\u2019s graduates joined the <em>Krypteia</em>, a secret police force which spied on and punished the helot class. For the point, name this rigorous education and military training protocol undergone by all non-slave men of Sparta.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Agoge</u></b></em> [[ah-GOH-geh]] (accept answers which appear phonetically similar; prompt on descriptive answers like \"education\" or \"military training\" for \"Spartan\" boys or men before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The State Council was created by this man, who created the category of Free Agriculturalists. After this man's advisor tried to reorganize the Masonic order, Mikhail Speranksy was made a scapegoat and tried with others including Fyodor Rostopchin. At the Congress of Erfurt, this man met Napoleon, and he signed the Treaty of Tilsit. This man fended off the French invasion of Russia and helped negotiate at the Congress of Vienna. For the point, name this Russian tsar who was succeeded by Nicholas I.", "answer": "<b><u>Alexander I</u></b> (prompt on \"Alexander\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Throughout his life, this musician showed a keen interest in folk music, working with his countryman Zoltan Kodaly [[KOH-dye]] to collect folk melodies from his native country. <em>Kossuth</em> [[KOHSH-oot]], an early piece by this composer, is a symphonic poem centered on the 1848 War of Independence in his country. This man's government pressured him to remove the name of Jewish librettist B\u00e9la Bal\u00e1sz [[bah-LOSH]] from his only opera, <em>Bluebeard's Castle</em>. For the point, what composer and ethnomusicologist is known for his collections of Hungarian folksongs?", "answer": "B\u00e9la <b><u>Bart\u00f3k</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man was followed at the Wheaton Plaza and Laurel Shopping center where he, Dora Thompson, and Nick Zarvos were shot by a man who forgot to shout \"A Penny For Your Thoughts.\" E. Howard Hunt was supposed to plant Democratic campaign material after Arthur Bremer shot this man, whose wife, Lurleen, was also a governor. This man ran with Curtis LeMay for president in 1968 and is known for his \"Stand in the Schoolhouse Door.\" For the point, name this Alabama politician who stood for \"segregation now, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever.\"", "answer": "George <b><u>Wallace</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man's wife, Mary Everest, was a fellow mathematician and the author of <em>Philosophy and Fun of Algebra</em>. This man\u2019s initial involvement in the school of logic was prompted by a debate between one of this man's supporters, Augustus De Morgan, and Sir William Hamilton. A 2003 article by John Corcoran provides a critical evaluation of the differences between Aristotelian logic and the system of logic created by this man. For the point, name this English mathematician, whose symbolic logic paved the way for modern computers.", "answer": "George <b><u>Boole</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Charles La Trobe's tax levy led to this event which included the Forest Creek Monster Meeting. This event led to the use of the secret ballot in the 1856 Electoral Act, which William Nicholson pioneered. The murder of James Scobie in this event led to the burning of Bentley's Hotel. This event followed the Red Ribbon Rebellion and the Bendigo Petition and included the creation of the Ballarat Reform League. Participants in this event formed the \"Diggers Congress.\" For the point, name this 1854 rebellion of gold miners which inspired Australian democracy.", "answer": "<b><u>Eureka</u></b> Stockade Rebellion (accept synonyms for \"Rebellion\" such as \"Revolution\" or \"Insurgency\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Sidney Smith helped defend this city in a 1799 siege, Napoleon's first decisive loss. A siege at this city was led by Guy of Lusignan who was himself besieged by Saladin before Richard I and Philip II of France came to their aid. Before fleeing the Levant, this city was the headquarters of the Knights Hospitaller. Gregory X was unable to raise a crusade to save this city from Sultan Qalawun of the Mamluks, thus ending the crusading movement when this city fell in 1291. For the point, name this city on Haifa Bay in Israel.", "answer": "<b><u>Acre</u></b> [[AH-ker]] or [[AY-ker]] (accept <b><u>Akko</u></b>; accept <b><u>Akka</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An assassin on whom this event was blamed was said to have met his victim at a bar called Le Boeuf sur le Toit. Three years after this event, a show trial for that assassin was scheduled during which former French foreign minister Georges Bonnet was to declare that \"world Jewry\" caused France's loss in World War Two. This event followed the Polenaktion and began when Herschel Grynszpan killed Ernst von Rath in Paris. More than 30 thousand Jewish men were sent to concentration camps after, for the point, what 1938 pogrom?", "answer": "<b><u>Kristallnacht</u></b> (accept <b><u>Night of Broken Glass</u></b>; accept <b><u>Crystal Night</u></b>; accept <b><u>November</u></b> Pogrom(s))", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A Democratic movement under this man was the Free Civil Right Movement which pursued revision of the Unequal Treaties. The Northern Alliance was established under this man's rule, in which he passed the Five Public Notices, which lasted until the Dajokan Proclamation. Anarchists tried to kill this man in the High Treason Incident, similar to the Red Flag Incident. This man abolished feudalism as part of the five-part Charter Oath of 1868. For the point, name this restored Japanese emperor who brought Japan to prominence.", "answer": "Emperor <b><u>Meiji</u></b> (accept in any order; accept <b><u>Meiji</u></b> the Great; accept <b><u>Meiji</u></b> the Good; accept <b><u>Mutsuhito</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1560, Giachem Bifrun published the first translation of the New Testament into this language. In 1982, an attempt to introduce a unified written form of this language was begun by linguist Heinrich Schmid, but that <em>Grischun</em> [[GREE-shoon]] amalgam has yet to be fully accepted. In 1996, this language was recognized by referendum, alongside German, Italian, and French, as one of the four official languages of Switzerland. For the point, name this Romance language.", "answer": "<b><u>Romansh</u></b> language", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The standing of this ethnoreligious group increased when Muhammad Ali abolished the <em>Jizya</em> tax. In 2012, Tawadros II was selected as the Patriarch of the See of St. Mark and, consequently, the head of this ethnoreligious group. In the 2nd century, the Gospels were translated to this ethnoreligious group\u2019s eponymous language, a descendant of Demotic, and enabled the establishment of the Church of Alexandria. For the point, name this North African ethnoreligious group, the largest Christian population in the Middle East.", "answer": "<b><u>Copt</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Copt</u></b>ic Christians or Church)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "According to Chinese sources, this structure was ruled by a queen with the body of two snakes. In the 19th century, this structure was popularized in the West in the writing of naturalist Henri Mouhot who said it was, \"Grander than anything left to us by Greece or Rome.\" This structure was legendarily built as a home to the god Precha Ket Mealea, a son of Indra, but it has historically been attributed to Suryavarman II, a 12th century Khmer king. For the point, name this Hindu-turned-Buddhist temple, located in Cambodia.", "answer": "<b><u>Angkor Wat</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Lion of Lucerne is a relief dedicated to this group and commemorating the massacre of its members during the 1792 storming of the Tuileries Palace. This military force was first led by Kaspar von Silenen during the 16th century War of Urbino and received its best known commission in 1503 from the former Cardinal Giuliano della Rovere. This unit sacrificed itself to allow Clement VII to escape during Charles V\u2019s sack of Rome. For the point, name this non-Italian military force tasked with the protection of the Catholic Pope.", "answer": "Pontifical <b><u>Swiss Guard</u></b> (accept Papal <b><u>Swiss Guard</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Augustus Pugin designed this structure for Charles Barry. David Boswell Reid, the \"grandfather of air-conditioning,\" put an air shaft in this structure, which stands over the Jubilee Line. Once named for St. Stephen, this structure contains the Prison Room in which Charles Bradlaugh was jailed for protesting a religious oath. Edmund Dickinson invented double three-legged gravity escarpments to keep time for this structure's clock. Located at the north end of the Palace of Westminster, for the point, what is this British clock tower?", "answer": "<b><u>Big Ben</u></b> (or <b><u>Elizabeth</u></b> Tower; accept <b><u>Clock</u></b> Tower of the Houses of <b><u>Parliament</u></b>; accept <b><u>Clock</u></b> Tower of <b><u>Westminster Palace</u></b> (or <b><u>Palace</u></b> of <b><u>Westminster</u></b>) before  mentioned; prompt on \"Clock Tower\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "An anarchist leader in this country was nicknamed Marusya, and an anarchist group in this country was known as Nabat. The film <em>Red Devils</em> has as its primary antagonist a leader from this country who led the Free Territory after capturing Huliaipole [[hoo-lee-uh-POH-lee]] . An anarchist state in what is now this country was founded by Nestor Makhno, and Stalin's brutal rule of this country included causing the death of millions by starvation via the Holodomor. For the point, name this country bordering Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>Ukraine</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The <em>boquerone</em> creator of this painting allowed strangers into a Paris studio to watch its creation, believing the publicity would help the antifascist cause. Work on this painting began, at the urging of the poet Juan Larrea, on May 1, 1937, just days after the event it depicts. This painting first appeared as a large mural for the Spanish pavilion at the 1937 World\u2019s Fair. For the point, name this painting by Pablo Picasso, which depicts the aftermath of a bombing in a Basque country town.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Guernica</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In a speech, this man called himself a \"victim of ignominious suspicions\" and begged his countrymen to \"remain united, lest you become the assassins of the country and your own executioners.\" Daniel F. O'Leary refused to destroy this man's papers, preserving evidence of his affair with Manuela S\u00e1enz. This man's militaristic legacy influenced the rule of the <em>caudillo</em> strongmen in Venezuela. In spite of this man's efforts, Gran Colombia dissolved into states like Ecuador and Colombia. For the point, name this South American \"Liberator.\"", "answer": "Sim\u00f3n <b><u>Bol\u00edvar</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}